<div1 id="intro" role="chapter1"><head>Introduction</head>
<!-- $Id: introduction.xml,v 1.43 2003/09/08 13:04:48 davidc Exp $ -->

<div2 id="intro_notation"><head>Mathematics and its Notation</head>

<p>A distinguishing feature of mathematics is the use of a complex and
highly evolved system of two-dimensional symbolic notations.  As
J.R.&nbsp;Pierce has written in his book on communication theory,
mathematics and its notations should not be viewed as one and the same
thing <bibref ref="Pierce1961"/>. Mathematical ideas exist independently of
the notations that represent them. However, the relation between meaning
and notation is subtle, and part of the power of mathematics to describe
and analyze derives from its ability to represent and manipulate ideas in
symbolic form. The challenge in putting mathematics on the World Wide Web
is to capture both notation and content (that is, meaning) in such a way
that documents can utilize the highly-evolved notational forms of written
and printed mathematics, and the potential for interconnectivity in
electronic media.</p>

<p>Mathematical notations are constantly evolving as people continue
to make innovations in ways of approaching and expressing ideas. Even
the commonplace notations of arithmetic have gone through an amazing
variety of styles, including many defunct ones advocated by leading
mathematical figures of their day <bibref ref="Cajori1928"/>. Modern
mathematical notation is the product of centuries of refinement, and
the notational conventions for high-quality typesetting are quite
complicated. For example, variables and letters which stand for
numbers are usually typeset today in a special mathematical italic
font subtly distinct from the usual text italic. Spacing around
symbols for operations such as +, -, &times; and / is slightly
different from that of text, to reflect conventions about operator
precedence. Entire books have been devoted to the conventions of
mathematical typesetting, from the alignment of superscripts and
subscripts, to rules for choosing parenthesis sizes, and on to
specialized notational practices for subfields of mathematics (for
instance, <bibref ref="Chaundy1954"/>, <bibref
ref="Swanson1979"/>, <bibref ref="Swanson1999"/>, <bibref
ref="Higham1993"/>, or in the &TeX; literature <bibref
ref="Knuth1986"/> and <bibref ref="Spivak1986"/>).</p>

<p>Notational conventions in mathematics, and in printed text in general,
guide the eye and make printed expressions much easier to read and
understand. Though we usually take them for granted, we rely on
hundreds of conventions such as paragraphs, capital letters, font
families and cases, and even the device of decimal-like numbering of
sections such as we are using in this document (an invention due to
G.&nbsp;Peano, who is probably better known for his axioms for the
natural numbers).  Such notational conventions are perhaps even more important
for electronic media, where one must contend with the difficulties of
on-screen reading.</p>

<p>However, there is more to putting mathematics on the Web
than merely finding ways of displaying traditional
mathematical notation in a Web browser. The Web represents a
fundamental change in the underlying metaphor for knowledge
storage, a change in which <emph>interconnectivity</emph>
plays a central role. It is becoming increasingly important to
find ways of communicating mathematics which facilitate
automatic processing, searching and indexing, and reuse in
other mathematical applications and contexts. With this
advance in communication technology, there is an opportunity
to expand our ability to represent, encode, and ultimately to
communicate our mathematical insights and understanding with
each other. We believe that MathML is an important step in
developing mathematics on the Web.</p>
</div2>

<div2 id="intro_origin"><head>Origins and Goals</head>

<div3><head>The History of MathML</head>

<p>The problem of encoding mathematics for computer processing
or electronic communication is much older than the Web. The
common practice among scientists before the Web was to write
papers in some encoded form based on the ASCII character set,
and e-mail them to each other. Several markup methods for
mathematics, in particular &TeX; <bibref ref="Knuth1986"/>,
were already in wide use in 1992 just before the Web rose to
prominence, <bibref ref="Poppelier1992"/>.</p>

<p>Since its inception, the Web has demonstrated itself to be
a very effective method of making information available to
widely separated groups of individuals. However, even though
the World Wide Web was initially conceived and implemented by
scientists for scientists, the possibilities for including
mathematical expressions in HTML has been very limited. At
present, most mathematics on the Web consists of text with
images of scientific notation (in <termdef id="td-gif"
term="Graphic Interchange Format">GIF</termdef> or <termdef
id="td-jpeg" term="Joint Photographic Exchange
Group">JPEG</termdef> format), which are difficult to read and
to author, or of entire documents in <termdef id="td-pdf"
term="Portable Document Format">PDF</termdef> form.</p> 

<p>The World Wide Web Consortium (W3C) recognized that lack of
support for scientific communication was a serious
problem. Dave Raggett included a proposal for HTML Math in the
HTML 3.0 working draft in 1994. A panel discussion on
mathematical markup was held at the WWW Conference in
Darmstadt in April 1995. In November 1995, representatives
from Wolfram Research presented a proposal for doing mathematics in
HTML to the W3C team. In May 1996, the Digital Library
Initiative meeting in Champaign-Urbana played an important
role in bringing together many interested parties. Following
the meeting, an HTML Math Editorial Review Board was
formed. In the intervening years, this group has grown, and
was formally reconstituted as the first W3C Math Working Group
in March 1997.  The second W3C Math Working Group was
chartered in July 1998 with a term which was later extended to run
to the end of the year 2000.</p>

<p>The MathML proposal reflects the interests and expertise of
a very diverse group. Many contributions to the development of
MathML deserve special mention, some of which we touch on
here. One such contribution concerns the question of
accessibility, especially for the visually handicapped.
T.&nbsp;V.&nbsp;Raman is particularly notable in this
regard. Neil Soiffer and Bruce Smith from Wolfram Research
shared their experience with the problems of representing
mathematics in connection with the design of Mathematica 3.0;
this expertise was an important influence in the design of the
presentation elements. Paul Topping from Design Science also
contributed his expertise in mathematical formatting and
editing. MathML has benefited from the participation of a
number of working group members involved in other mathematical
encoding efforts in the <termdef id="td-sgml" term="Standard
Generalized Markup Language">SGML</termdef> and
computer-algebra communities, including Stephen Buswell from
Stilo Technologies, Nico Poppelier at first with Elsevier
Science, St&eacute;phane Dalmas from INRIA (Sophia Antipolis),
Stan Devitt at first with Waterloo Maple, Angel Diaz and
Robert S.&nbsp;Sutor from IBM, and Stephen M.&nbsp;Watt from
the University of Western Ontario. In particular, MathML has
been influenced by the OpenMath project, the work of the ISO
12083 working group, and Stilo Technologies' work on a
<quote>semantic</quote> mathematics DTD fragment. The American
Mathematical Society has played a key role in the development
of MathML. Among other things, it has provided two working
group chairs: Ron Whitney led the group from May 1996 to March
1997, and Patrick Ion, who has co-chaired the group with
Robert Miner from The Geometry Center from March 1997 to 
June 1998, and since July 1998 with Angel Diaz of IBM.</p>

</div3>


<div3><head>Limitations of HTML</head>

<p>The demand for effective means of electronic scientific
communication remains high. Ever increasingly, researchers,
scientists, engineers, educators, students and technicians
find themselves working at dispersed locations and relying on
electronic communication. At the same time, the image-based
methods that are currently the predominant means of
transmitting scientific notation over the Web are primitive
and inadequate. Document quality is poor, authoring is
difficult, and mathematical information contained in images is
not available for searching, indexing, or reuse in other
applications.</p>

<p>The most obvious problems with HTML for mathematical
communication are of two types.</p>

<p><emph>Display Problems.</emph> Consider the equation
<graphic role="inline" valign="bottom"
source="image/f1001.gif" alt="2^{2^x} = 10"/>.  This equation
is sized to match the surrounding line in 14pt type on the
system where it was authored. Of course, on other systems, or
for other font sizes, the equation is too small or too
large. A second point to observe is that the equation image
was generated against a white background. Thus, if a reader or
browser resets the page background to another color, the
anti-aliasing in the image results in white
<quote>halos</quote>. Next, consider the equation <graphic
role="inline" valign="bottom" source="image/f1002.gif"
alt="x=\frac{-b\pm\sqrt{b^2-4ac}}{2a}"/>, which is an example
with the equation's horizontal alignment axis above the tops
of the lower-case letters in the surrounding text.</p>

<p>This equation has a descender which places the baseline for
the equation  at a  point about  a third of  the way  from the
bottom of the image. One can pad the image like this: 
<graphic role="inline" source="image/f1003.gif"
alt="x=\frac{-b\pm\sqrt{b^2-4ac}}{2a}"/>,     
so that  the centerline of the  image and the  baseline of the
equation   coincide,  but  this   causes  problems   with  the
inter-line  spacing,   resulting  in  the   equation  becoming
difficult to  read.  Moreover,  center alignment of  images is
handled  in  slightly different  ways  by different  browsers,
making  it  impossible   to  guarantee  proper  alignment  for
different clients.</p>

<p>Image-based equations are generally harder to see, read and
comprehend   than  the   surrounding  text   in   the  browser
window.  Moreover,  these   problems  become  worse  when  the
document is printed. The resolution of the equations as images
will be  around 70 dots  per inch, while the  surrounding text
will  typically  be  300,  600  or more  dots  per  inch.  The
disparity  in quality  is judged  to be  unacceptable  by most
people.</p>

<p><emph>Encoding  Problems.</emph> Consider trying  to search
this  document  for part  of  an  equation,  for example,  the
<quote>=10</quote> from the first equation above. In a similar
vein,  consider  trying to  cut  and  paste  an equation  into
another application; even more demanding is to cut and paste a
sub-expression.  Using  image-based methods, neither  of these
common needs can be  adequately addressed. Although the use of
the <kw>alt</kw> attribute in the document  source can help, it is clear
that  highly interactive  Web  documents must  provide a  more
sophisticated  interface  between  browsers  and  mathematical
notation.</p>

<p>Another problem with encoding mathematics as images is that
it requires more bandwidth.  Markup describing an equation is
typically smaller and more compressible than an image of the
equation.  In addition, by using markup-based encoding, more
of the rendering process is moved to the client machine.</p>
</div3>

<div3><head>Requirements for Mathematics Markup</head>

<p>Some display problems associated with including
mathematical notation in HTML documents as images could be
addressed by improving image handling by browsers. However,
even if image handling were improved, the problem of making
the information contained in mathematical expressions
available to other applications would remain.  Therefore, in
planning for the future, it is not sufficient merely to
upgrade image-based methods.  To integrate mathematical
material fully into Web documents, a markup-based encoding of
mathematical notation and content is required.</p>

<p>In designing any markup language, it is essential to
consider carefully the needs of its potential users.  In the
case of MathML, the needs of potential users cover a broad
spectrum, from education to research, and on to commerce.</p>

<p>The education community is a large and important group that
must be able to put scientific curriculum materials on the
Web. At the same time, educators often have limited time and
equipment, and are severely hampered by the difficulty of
authoring technical Web documents. Students and teachers need
to be able to create mathematical content quickly and easily,
using intuitive, easy-to-learn, low-cost tools.</p>

<p>Electronic textbooks are another way of using the Web which will
potentially be very important in education. Management consultant
Peter Drucker has prophesied the end of big-campus residential higher
education and its distribution over the Web.  Electronic textbooks
will need to be interactive, allowing intercommunication between the
text and scientific software and graphics.</p>

<p>The academic and commercial research communities generate large
volume of dense scientific material.  Increasingly, research
publications are being stored in databases, such as the highly
successful <loc href="http://xxx.lanl.gov">physics and mathematics
preprint server and archive</loc> at Los Alamos National
Laboratory. This is especially true in some areas of physics and
mathematics where academic journal prices have been increasing at an
unsustainable rate.  In addition, databases of information on
mathematical research, such as <loc
href="http://www.ams.org/mathscinet">Mathematical Reviews</loc> and
<loc href="http://www.zblmath.fiz-karlsruhe.de">Zentralblatt f&uuml;r
Mathematik</loc>, offer millions of records on the Web containing
mathematics.</p>

<p>To accommodate the research community, a design for
mathematical markup must facilitate the maintenance and
operation of large document collections, for which automatic
searching and indexing are important.  Because of the large
collection of legacy documents containing mathematics, especially in
&TeX;, the ability to convert between existing formats and any
new one is also very important to the research community.
Finally, the ability to maintain information for archival
purposes is vital to academic research.</p>

<p>Corporate  and academic scientists  and engineers  also use
technical documents  in their  work to collaborate,  to record
results of experiments and computer simulations, and to verify
calculations.  For  such uses,  mathematics  on  the Web  must
provide  a standard  way of  sharing information  that  can be
easily read, processed and generated using commonly available,
easy-to-use tools.</p>

<p>Another general design requirement is the ability to render
mathematical  material  in  other  media  such  as  speech  or
braille,  which  is   extremely  important  for  the  visually
impaired.</p>

<p>Commercial publishers are also involved with mathematics on
the Web at all levels  from electronic versions of print books
to  interactive textbooks  and academic  journals.  Publishers
require a  method of  putting mathematics on  the Web  that is
capable of high-quality  output, robust enough for large-scale
commercial use, and preferably compatible with their previous,
often SGML-based, production systems.</p>
</div3>

<div3 id="intro_goals"><head>Design Goals of MathML</head>

<p>In  order  to meet  the  diverse  needs  of the  scientific
community,  MathML  has   been  designed  with  the  following
ultimate goals in mind.</p>

<p>MathML should:
<ulist>
<item>
<p>Encode mathematical material suitable for teaching
and scientific communication at all levels.</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>Encode both mathematical notation and mathematical meaning.</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>Facilitate conversion to and from other mathematical
formats, both presentational and semantic. Output formats should include:
<ulist>
<item>
<p>graphical displays</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>speech synthesizers</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>input for computer algebra systems</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>other mathematics typesetting languages, such as &TeX;</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>plain text displays, e.g. VT100 emulators</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>print media, including braille</p>
</item>
</ulist>
</p>
<p>It is recognized that conversion to and from other notational
systems or media may entail loss of information in the process.</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>Allow the passing of information intended for
specific renderers and applications.</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>Support efficient browsing of lengthy expressions.</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>Provide for extensibility.</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>Be well suited to template and other mathematics editing techniques.</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>Be human legible, and simple for software to generate and process.</p>
</item>
</ulist>
</p>

<p>No matter how successfully  MathML may achieve its goals as
a markup language, it is clear that MathML will only be useful
if it is  implemented well. To this end,  the W3C Math Working
Group has identified a short list of additional implementation
goals. These  goals attempt to describe  concisely the minimal
functionality MathML rendering  and processing software should
try to provide.
</p>

<ulist>

<item>
<p>MathML expressions in HTML (and XHTML) pages should render
properly in popular Web browsers, in accordance with reader and author
viewing preferences, and at the highest quality possible given the
capabilities of the platform.</p></item>

<item>
<p>HTML (and XHTML) documents containing MathML expressions should
print properly and at high-quality printer resolutions.</p></item>

<item>
<p>MathML expressions  in Web pages  should be able to  react to
user  gestures, such  those as  with a  mouse,  and to coordinate
communication    with   other    applications    through   the
browser.</p></item>

<item>
<p>Mathematical expression editors and converters should be developed
to facilitate the creation of Web pages containing MathML
expressions.</p></item>

</ulist>

<p>These goals have begun to be addressed for the near term by using embedded
elements such as Java applets, plug-ins and ActiveX controls to render
MathML. However, the extent to which these goals are ultimately met depends on the
cooperation and support of browser vendors, and other software developers. The W3C
Math Working Group has continued to work with the working groups for the Document
Object Model (DOM) and the Extensible Style Language (XSL) to ensure that the
needs of the scientific community will be met in the future, and feels that MathML
2.0 shows considerable progress in this area over the situation that obtained at
the time of the MathML 1.0 Recommendation (April 1998) <bibref diff="add"
ref="MathML1"/>.</p>

</div3>

</div2>

<div2 id="intro_role"><head>The Role of MathML on the Web</head>

<div3><head>Layered Design of Mathematical Web Services</head>

<p>The design  goals of MathML  require a system  for encoding
mathematical  material  for  the  Web which  is  flexible  and
extensible, suitable  for interaction with  external software,
and  capable of  producing high-quality  rendering  in several
media. Any markup language  that encodes enough information to
do  all  these  tasks  well  will of  necessity  involve  some
complexity.</p>

<p>At the same time, it  is important for many groups, such as
students, to  have simple ways  to include mathematics  in Web
pages  by hand.  Similarly,  other groups,  such as  the &TeX;
community, would be best served  by a system which allowed the
direct entry of markup languages like &TeX; into Web pages. In
general, specific user groups are better served by specialized
kinds of input and output tailored to their needs.  Therefore,
the  ideal system  for  communicating mathematics  on the  Web
should provide both specialized services for input and output,
and  general  services  for  interchange  of  information  and
rendering to multiple media.</p>

<p>In practical terms, the observation that mathematics on the
Web  should provide  for  both specialized  and general  needs
naturally  leads to the  idea of  a layered  architecture. One
layer consists of powerful, general software tools exchanging,
processing and rendering suitably encoded mathematical data. A
second layer consists of  specialized software tools, aimed at
specific user  groups, which are capable  of easily generating
encoded  mathematical data  that can  then be  shared  with a
particular audience.</p>

<p>MathML is designed to  provide the encoding of mathematical
information for the bottom,  more general layer in a two-layer
architecture. It is intended  to encode complex notational and
semantic    structure   in    an   explicit,    regular,   and
easy-to-process  way  for  renderers, searching  and  indexing
software, and other mathematical applications.</p>

<p>As a consequence, raw MathML markup is <emph>not</emph>
primarily intended for direct use by authors. While MathML is
human-readable, which helps a lot in debugging it, in all but
the simplest cases it is too verbose and error-prone for hand
generation.  Instead, it is anticipated that authors will use
equation editors, conversion programs, and other specialized
software tools to generate MathML.  Alternatively, some
renderers and systems supporting mathematics may convert other
kinds of input directly included in Web pages into MathML on
the fly, in response to a cut-and-paste operation, for
example.</p>

<p>In  some  ways, MathML  is  analogous  to other  low-level,
communication formats such as Adobe's PostScript language. You
can create PostScript files in a variety of ways, depending on
your  needs; experts write  and modify  them by  hand, authors
create  them  with   word  processors,  graphic  artists  with
illustration programs,  and so on. Once you  have a PostScript
file, however,  you can share  it with a very  large audience,
since devices  which render  PostScript, such as  printers and
screen previewers, are widely available.</p>

<p>Part  of  the  reason  for  designing MathML  as  a  markup
language for  a low-level, general, communication  layer is to
stimulate mathematical  Web software development  in the layer
above. MathML  provides a way of  coordinating the development
of modular  authoring tools and rendering  software. By making
it easier  to develop a  functional piece of a  larger system,
MathML  can   stimulate  a  <quote>critical   mass</quote>  of
software  development,  greatly to  the  benefit of  potential
users of mathematics on the Web.</p>

<p>One can envision a similar situation for mathematical data.
Authors are  free to create  MathML documents using  the tools
best  suited to  their  needs. For  example,  a student  might
prefer to use a menu-driven equation editor that can write out
MathML to  an XHTML  file.  A researcher  might use  a computer
algebra  package that  automatically encodes  the mathematical
content of  an expression, so  that it can  be cut from  a Web
page  and  evaluated  by  a colleague.   An  academic  journal
publisher might  use a program  that converts &TeX;  markup to
HTML and MathML. Regardless of the method used to create a Web
page containing MathML, once  it exists, all the advantages of
a powerful and general communication layer become available. A
variety of  MathML software  could all be  used with  the same
document to  render it  in speech  or print, to  send it  to a
computer algebra  system, or to manage  it as part  of a large
Web  document  collection.   To  render  high-quality  printed
mathematics the  MathML encoding will often  be converted back
to standard  typesetting and composition  languages, including
&TeX; which is widely appreciated  for the job it does in this
regard. Finally, one may expect that eventually MathML will be
integrated  into  other  arenas  where  mathematical  formulas
occur,   such  as   spreadsheets,  statistical   packages  and
engineering tools.</p>

<p>The W3C Math Working Group has been working with vendors to ensure
that a variety of MathML software will soon be available, including
both rendering and authoring tools. A current list of MathML software
is maintained on the <loc href="http://www.w3.org/Math/">public Math
page at the World Wide Web Consortium</loc>.</p>
</div3>

<div3><head>Relation to Other Web Technology</head>

<p>The original  conception  of an  HTML  Math  was  a  simple,
straightforward  extension  to  HTML  that would  be  natively
implemented  in   browsers.   However,  very   early  on,  the
explosive  growth of  the Web  made  it clear  that a  general
extension  mechanism was  required, and  that  mathematics was
only one of many kinds  of structured data which would have to
be integrated into the Web using such a mechanism.</p>

<p>Given that MathML must integrate into the Web as an
extension, it is extremely important that MathML, and MathML
software, can interact well with the existing Web environment.
In particular, MathML has been designed with three kinds of
interaction in mind. First, in order to create mathematical
Web content, it is important that existing mathematical markup
languages can be converted to MathML, and that existing
authoring tools can be modified to generate MathML.  Second,
it must be possible to embed MathML markup seamlessly in HTML
markup, as it evolves, in such a way that it will be
accessible to future browsers, search engines, and all the
kinds of Web applications which now manipulate HTML.  Finally,
it must be possible to render MathML embedded in HTML in
today's Web browsers in some fashion, even if it is less than
ideal.  As HTML evolves into XHTML, all the preceding requirements
become increasingly needed.</p>

<p id="intro_bidi">The World Wide Web is a fully international and 
collaborative movement.  Mathematics is a language used all 
over the world.  The mathematical notation in science
and engineering is embedded in a matrix of local natural 
languages.  The W3C strives to be a constructive force
in the spread of possibilities for communication throughout
the world.  Therefore MathML will encounter problems
of internationalization.  This version of MathML is
not knowingly incompatible with the needs of languages
which are written from left to right.  However the
default orientation of MathML 2 is left-to-right, and
it is clear that the needs for the writing of
mathematical formulas embedded in some natural languages
may not yet be met.  So-called bi-directional technology
is still in development, and better support for formulas
in that context must be a matter for future developers.
</p>

<div4><head>Existing Mathematical Markup Languages</head>

<p>Perhaps the most important influence on mathematical markup
languages of the last two decades is the &TeX; typesetting
system developed by Donald Knuth <bibref ref="Knuth1986"/>.
&TeX; is a de facto standard in the mathematical research
community, and it is pervasive in the scientific community at
large.  &TeX; sets a standard for quality of visual rendering,
and a great deal of effort has gone into ensuring MathML can
provide the same visual rendering quality.  Moreover, because
of the many legacy documents in &TeX;, and because of the
large authoring community versed in &TeX;, a priority in the
design of MathML was the ability to convert &TeX; mathematics
input into MathML format.  The feasibility of such conversion
has been demonstrated by prototype software.</p>

<p>Extensive work on encoding mathematics has also been done
in the SGML community, and SGML-based encoding schemes are
widely used by commercial publishers.  ISO 12083 is an
important markup language which contains a DTD fragment
primarily intended for describing the visual presentation of
mathematical notation. Because ISO 12083 mathematical notation
and its derivatives share many presentational aspects with
&TeX;, and because SGML enforces structure and regularity more
than &TeX;, much of the work in ensuring MathML is compatible
with &TeX; also applies well to ISO 12083.</p>

<p>MathML also pays particular attention to compatibility with
other mathematical software, and in particular, with computer
algebra systems.  Many of the presentation elements of MathML
are derived in part from the mechanism of typesetting
boxes. The MathML content elements are heavily indebted to the
OpenMath project and the work by Stilo Technologies on a
mathematical DTD fragment. The OpenMath project has close ties
to both the SGML and computer algebra communities, and has
laid a foundation for an SGML- and XML-based means of
communication between mathematical software packages, amongst
other things.  The feasibility of both generating and
interpreting MathML in computer algebra systems has been
demonstrated by prototype software.</p>

</div4>

<div4><head>HTML Extension Mechanisms</head>

<p>As noted above, the success of HTML has led to enormous
pressure to incorporate a wide variety of data types and
software applications into the Web.  Each new format or
application potentially places new demands on HTML and on
browser vendors. For some time, it has been clear that a
general extension mechanism is necessary to accommodate new
extensions to HTML. At the very beginning, the working group
began its work thinking of a plain extension to HTML in the
spirit of the first mathematics support suggested for HTML
3.2.  But for a good number of reasons, once we got into the
details, this proved to be not so good an idea.  Since work
first began on MathML, XML <bibref ref="XML"/>,
has emerged as the dominant such
general extension mechanism.</p>

<p>XML stands for Extensible Markup Language.  It is designed as a
simplified version of SGML, the meta-language used to define the
grammar and syntax of HTML. One of the goals of XML is to be suitable
for use on the Web, and in the context of this discussion it can be
viewed as the general mechanism for extending HTML. As its name
implies, extensibility is a key feature of XML; authors are free to
declare and use new elements and attributes. At the same time, XML
grammar and syntax rules carefully enforce regular document structure
to facilitate automatic processing and maintenance of large document
collections. Mathematically speaking XML is essentially a notation for
decorated rooted planar trees, and thus of great generality as an
encoding tool. </p>

<p>Since the setting up of the first W3C Math Working Group,
XML has garnered broad industry support, including that of
major browser vendors. The migration of HTML to an XML form
has been important to the W3C, and has resulted in the XHTML
Recommendation which delivers a new modularized form of HTML.
MathML can be viewed as another module which fits very well
with the new XHTML.  Indeed in <specref ref="parsing_module"/>
there is a new DTD for mathematics which is the result of
collaboration with the W3C HTML Working Group.</p>

<p>Furthermore, other applications of XML for all kinds of
document publishing and processing promise to become
increasingly important. Consequently, both on theoretical and
pragmatic grounds, it has made a great deal of sense to
specify MathML as an XML application.</p>

</div4>

<div4><head>Browser Extension Mechanisms</head>

<p>By now,  as opposed  to the situation  when the  
<phrase diff="chg">MathML 1.0 Recommendation <bibref diff="add" ref="MathML1"/></phrase> was adopted, the
details of  a general model  for rendering and  processing XML
extensions to  HTML are largely  clear. Formatting Properties,
developed  by  the   Cascading  Style  Sheets  and  Formatting
Properties Working  Group for  CSS and made  available through
the  Document Object Model  (DOM), will  be applied  to MathML
elements to obtain stylistic  control over the presentation of
MathML.   Further development  of these  Formatting Properties
falls within the  charters of both the CSS&amp;FP  and the XSL
working  groups.  For an  introduction to  this topic  see the
discussion   in   <specref   ref="interf"/>.    For   detailed
commentary  on  how  to  render MathML  with  current  systems
consult      the 
<loc href="http://www.w3.org/Math/">W3C Math WG Home Page</loc>.</p>

<p>Until  style  sheet mechanisms  are  capable of  delivering
native browser  rendering of MathML, however,  it is necessary
to extend  browser capabilities by using  embedded elements to
render MathML. It is already possible to instruct a browser to
use  a particular  embedded renderer  to process  embedded XML
markup such as MathML,  and to coordinate the resulting output
with the surrounding Web page, however the results are not yet
entirely as one wishes. See  <specref ref="interf"/>.</p>

<p>For  specialized  processing,   such  as  connecting  to  a
computer  algebra system,  the  capability of  calling out  to
other programs is likely to remain highly desirable.  However,
for  such an  interaction  to be  really  satisfactory, it  is
necessary  to define a  document object  model rich  enough to
facilitate  complicated   interactions  between  browsers  and
embedded elements. For this reason, the W3C Math Working Group
has coordinated  its efforts closely with  the Document Object
Model  (DOM)  Working Group.   The  results  are described  in
<specref ref="dom-intro"/>.</p>

<p>For    processing   by    embedded   elements,    and   for
inter-communication  between scientific software  generally, a
style  sheet-based layout  model  is in  some  ways less  than
ideal. It can impose  an additional implementation burden in a
setting  where it  may offer  few advantages,  and  it imposes
implementation requirements  for coordination between browsers
and embedded renderers that  will likely be unavailable in the
immediate future.</p>

<p>For  these  reasons, the  MathML  specification defines  an
attribute-based layout model,  which has proven very effective
for   high-quality  rendering   of   complicated  mathematical
expressions  in several  independent  implementations.  MathML
presentation  attributes  utilize  W3C  Formatting  Properties
where   possible.    Also,   MathML   elements    accept   <att>class</att>, <att>style</att> and <att>id</att> attributes to  facilitate their use with
CSS style sheets. However,  at present, there are few settings
where   CSS  machinery  is   currently  available   to  MathML
renderers. </p>

<p>The use of CSS style sheet mechanisms has been mentioned
above.  The mechanisms of XSL have also recently become
available for the transformation of XML documents to effect
their rendering.  Indeed the alternative forms of this present
recommendation, including the definitive public HTML version,
have been prepared from an underlying XML source using XSL
transformation language tools.  As further developments in
this direction become available to MathML, it is anticipated
their use will become the dominant method of stylistic control
of MathML presentation meant for use in rendering environments
which support those mechanisms.</p>
</div4>
</div3>
</div2>
</div1>



